- Help us , Father , help us ! - What about some food ?
- Father , they 're starving us ! - Are you staying , Father ?
This man is raving .
Are you sure you wish to see him on your own ?
A visitor for you , Baron Frankenstein .
If you need any assistance , I shall be outside .
They told me you wanted to see me .
Is it spiritual comfort you want ? Is that it ?
Keep your spiritual comfort for those who think they need it .
I sent for you because I could think of nobody else .
People trust you .
They listen to what you tell them .
Now listen to me , and when I 've finished you can pass it on to them .
Then , perhaps , they 'll believe me .
- I have to tell you ... - I have to tell you , you just listen !
I 'm sorry . If you think my word will carry any authority , I 'm afraid you are mistaken .
You 'd better not tell me what you consider so important .
- You 'll stay . - Take your hands off me .
- Tell me you 'll stay . - Do you want me to call the guard ?
I apologize . Please , sit down .
I said I apologize . I 'll not forget myself again .
As you wish .
Unless I can convince you ...
that what I 'm about to tell you is the absolute truth ...
then in one hour from now I shall be dead .
- I 've told you ... - Then , perhaps , you 'll understand .
Perhaps you 'd better start from the beginning .
Where did it all begin ?
I suppose it was when I was a boy at school .
I always had a brilliant intellect .
That fool who taught us may have been able to hoodwink the others ...
but what did he know ?
He 'd been teaching the same rubbish for 30 years ...
and I don 't suppose he 'd read a new book for 20 of those .
When my mother died , I inherited the Frankenstein fortune .
This enabled me to begin the life and work I had always planned for myself .
Victor , dear boy ...
you are the sole remaining member of the Frankenstein family .
I know you will conduct yourself ...
in a manner which would make your poor , dear mother proud of you .
I shall do my best , Uncle . Thank you .
Thank you all for coming .
Goodbye .
What was it you wished to see me about , Aunt Sophie ?
It is a matter of some delicacy , Victor . I ...
Was it about the allowance my mother made you ?
You needn 't worry . I shall continue to pay it .
You 're a good boy , Victor . Your poor mother would be proud ...
- Yes , yes . - Elizabeth , thank your cousin .
There 's really no need .
Come along , Elizabeth . Say thank you , nicely .
Thank you .
She 's a good girl . She 'll grow into a fine woman one day .
- I 'm sure she will . - And she 'll make someone a good wife .
- Goodbye . - Well , goodbye .
The first of the month , your mother used to ...
- I understand . I shall do the same . - Thank you .
Good morning .
Is this the home of the Frankenstein family ?
It is .
I 'm Paul Krempe . I have an appointment with Baron Frankenstein .
You must be Victor . I 'm going to be your tutor .
So I understand .
But surely it isn 't settled yet .
I thought this was just an interview to decide ...
whether you were suitable for the position .
Yes , but I 've had correspondence with the Baron ...
and he seemed satisfied with my qualifications .
That 's right , he did , didn 't he ?
- I expect he wanted to see what I look like . - That must have been it .
- Will you tell your father that I 'm here ? - My father is dead .
- That 's ridiculous . I had a letter ... - He 's been dead for 10 years .
It was I who advertised for a tutor . It was I who wrote to you .
You 're the Baron then , are you ?
And have been since I was 5 years old .
And you want a tutor for your son ?
I thought it would save a lot of explanation by letter .
A difficult thing at the best of times .
I fail to see that the disclosure of the facts can make any difference .
You were to be engaged as my tutor , subject to the Baron 's approval .
You will take up the position . You will be paid as arranged .
By whom ?
By the Baron . I 'm quite rich .
Do you still want the position ?
I should be honored , Herr Baron .
My first opinion of Paul was soon confirmed .
He turned out to be an admirable tutor .
In two years I 'd learned all he had to teach , but we went on together ...
probing into the unknown , investigating , recording , searching ...
always searching ...
until gradually the sweep of our research began to assume a single direction ...
and to this aim we finally turned all our energies .
It took us years of unrelenting work to discover what we were seeking .
Then , one night ...
out of sight and sound of the rest of the house ...
our efforts were rewarded .
Paul , it 's alive .
Paul , we 've done it !
There was a lag between the cardiac reaction and the first visible signs of life .
That 'll be the time required for the heart to circulate blood through the entire body .
If we could delay or prolong the period in which the body is apparently dead ...
while the heart is alive ...
we 'd have a living body with only the barest life-spark present .
Think what that would mean when it came to performing major surgery !
We could save hundreds of lives .
Reducing shock to a minimum , no loss of blood .
Victor , the Medical Federation meets next month in Berne .
Can we have our paper ready ?
We could .
- But we 're not going to . - Why not ?
It doesn 't meet again for a year . Why wait that long ?
We must wait .
What we 've done up to now is nothing to what we will do .
We 've only just started . Just opened the door .
Now is the time to go through that door and find what lies beyond it .
Don 't you see , Paul ? We 've discovered the source of life itself ...
and have used it to restore a creature that was dead .
This is a tremendous discovery , but we mustn 't share it yet .
We must move on to the next stage .
We 've restored life where life was extinct .
It 's no longer sufficient to bring the dead back to life .
We must create from the beginning . We must build up our own creature ...
and build it up from nothing .
From what ? What on earth are you talking about ?
Forget the whole . Now we must take the parts ...
limbs , organs , and then we must build .
- Build what ? - The most complex thing known to man :
Man himself .
We must create a human being ...
with perfect physique , hands of an artist , and a matured brain of a genius .
- We can do it . Don 't you see ? - No , I don 't .
What you 're saying is nonsense , a revolt against nature .
Such a thing could only end in evil .
Come , what 's the matter with you ? You haven 't shown any scruples up to now .
As for revolting against nature , haven 't we done so already and succeeded ?
Isn 't the thing that 's dead supposed to be dead for all time ?
Yet we brought it back to life .
We hold in the palms of our hands secrets that have never been dreamed of .
Where nature puts up barriers to confine the scope of man , we 've broken through !
- There 's nothing to stop us now . - What is it you want to do ?
First we need the framework , the body .
Last week they hanged a man at Engelstadt , a highwayman .
He 'd been terrifying the countryside for months . As a warning to others ...
his body has been left on a gibbet , just outside the town .
It 'll hang there till it rots ...
or it 's stolen .
The birds didn 't waste much time , did they ?
The eyes ...
Half the head is eaten away .
What are you going to do ?
Take the head off . It 's no use to me anyway .
It 's in the acid . A few minutes , and there 'll be no trace .
Paul , give me a hand with his clothes , will you ?
Look at those hands .
Great clodhopping things . No wonder he was a robber .
With hands like those , he couldn 't have been anything else .
Except , perhaps , a gorilla .
I don 't think we should continue with this .
We should wait and present our findings at the Federation .
- Should anything go wrong ... - I 've got it .
- What ? - Look after things while I 'm gone .
Gone where ?
If I leave tonight , I should get back by tomorrow evening .
- Victor ! - Yes , Paul , what is it ?
What are you talking about ? Where are you going ?
Going ?
I 'm going away for a little while . I 'll tell you about it when I get back .
Better not touch our friend here while I 'm gone . Let him rest in peace ...
while he can . Let 's have some food , I 'm hungry .
I thought it was the master .
No , he hasn 't come back yet , Justine .
Will he be in time for dinner , sir ?
I don 't know , he didn 't say .
There he is now , sir .
Good evening , Baron Frankenstein is expecting me . May I come in ?
I shall need some assistance with my luggage .
- Luggage ? - Yes , I 'm coming to stay .
Well , I 'm sorry , miss , but the Baron told no one of this .
But he must have done . I wrote him some weeks ago .
Victor , how happy I am to see you .
I 'm afraid there 's some mistake .
Mistake ?
Didn 't you get my letter ?
I 'm not Victor , I 'm Paul Krempe .
Oh , Paul Krempe . I 'm so sorry .
- I haven 't seen Victor for so long . - Now that you know who I am ...
why not tell me who you are ?
I 'm Elizabeth , Victor 's cousin . Didn 't he tell you about me ?
No , he did not .
For which he will be severely reprimanded when he returns .
- Oh , he 's away ? - He 's expected back at any moment .
We shan 't have long to wait .
Are you going to stay with us long ?
I 'm coming to live here .
- This is to be my home . - Live here ? But ...
Paul , I ...
Elizabeth .
Victor .
I received your letter . I was so sorry to hear about your mother .
How are you , my dear ?
The maid will show you to your room .
Paul , come see what I 've got . Elizabeth , we 'll see you at dinner .
- Yes , but ... - Paul , come on .
As he said , we will see you at dinner .
Lock the door , Paul . Come and look at these .
What about these ? Have you ever seen anything so beautiful ?
Bardello 's hands .
The hands of the world 's greatest sculptor .
Where did you get them ?
Leipzig . I heard that Bardello died there last week .
- All it needed was a little bribery . - You realize what this means ?
It means that our friend will have the finest hands any man ever possessed .
I mean your cousin 's arrival .
We can 't continue with this experiment . Not here , anyway .
- What are you talking about ? - Elizabeth . She might find out .
What if she does ? Where 's the harm ?
She 's young , Victor .
Her mind would be incapable of receiving such a shock .
All right ! You can 't see the horror of what you 're doing .
At first I was blind to it .
And now ?
While you were away , I decided I could not continue with this experiment .
I hope I can convince you I 'm right , change your mind , too .
You 'll never do that , Paul .
In six months , you 'll rejoice in the fact ...
you helped make this discovery . You 'll be as famous as I.
No , Victor . Infamous ! I will not help you , not anymore .
I beseech you .
Give this up , if not for your own sake , for the sake of the girl .
You 're wasting your time , Paul .
Help me graft these hands on . I want to see if they take .
Can 't you understand ? I will not help you anymore .
And I shall try to make Elizabeth leave here .
Elizabeth won 't leave , Paul .
If you 're really not going to help me , I 'd be glad if you 'd leave me alone .
I have work to do .
I shan 't be down for dinner . Make my excuses to Elizabeth , will you ?
- Will you require anything else ? - No , thank you , that will be all .
Very well , sir .
I shall take the master 's dinner up now .
Leave it outside the door .
Of course , Herr Krempe , I always do .
Do you take your coffee black or white , Paul ?
Elizabeth , I don 't know you very well , but I want you to do something for me .
Yes ?
Leave here .
Leave ?
Leave this house at once , and never come back .
That 's impossible . Why do you ask it ?
I can 't explain , but it will not be safe here .
Not safe ?
Victor will be here , won 't he ?
- Oh , yes . Victor will be here . - Then I fail to see ...
It 's because of Victor that I 'm asking you to leave .
He 's conducting experiments which could be very dangerous .
What sort of experiments ?
- You wouldn 't understand . - I would understand , I 'm sure .
Please , tell me .
Believe me , I can 't tell you , I would if I could .
Then I shall have to ask Victor .
If I 'm to marry him , then I have a right to know .
Marry ?
Of course , we 're engaged . Didn 't he tell you ?
How can you be engaged to someone you don 't even know ?
It was an arrangement between Victor and my mother .
That 's absurd . You can 't be expected to honor an arrangement of that sort .
My mother and I were entirely dependent upon Victor .
We 'd have starved without him .
Now , perhaps , you understand .
I understand you 're confusing gratitude with affection .
You have no right to speak to me like that . How dare you !
I 'm sorry . It 's entirely your own affair and nothing to do with me .
I still think you should leave . Believe me , it 's for your own good .
Really , Paul , I can 't imagine why you make this idiotic request .
It is not a request .
It 's a demand . You must not stay here .
Perhaps we should let Victor decide that . After all , it is his house .
Or had you forgotten ?
No , I haven 't forgotten .
I 'm sorry . Perhaps I shouldn 't have spoken to you like this .
I 'm sorry , too .
I lost my temper . Please , forgive me .
Really , Paul ...
just because it was arranged years ago ...
that 's no reason for my not marrying Victor .
It has always been my dearest wish .
His , too .
Victor ...
- How many times have I told you ? - Baron , then .
- Herr Baron . - That 's better .
How much longer is this to go on ?
Meeting like this in dark corridors . Making love in secret .
When are you going to marry me ?
What makes you so sure that I 'll marry you ?
Because you promised . And because of this .
Herr Baron Victor ...
this woman ...
what is she doing here ?
- Are you jealous ? - No .
Yes .
Yes , I am jealous .
She 's not your mistress ?
- If I thought she was ... - On the contrary , Justine .
She 's to be your mistress .
It will be your duty to serve my cousin Elizabeth .
And see to her every need as thoroughly as you have mine .
- In a different way of course . - Of course .
Victor , you 're not going away again , are you ?
I 'm afraid I must . I 'll be back tomorrow evening .
Why , Elizabeth ...
what 's the matter ?
I 'm disappointed . I see so little of you these days .
And there are the household accounts . You should check them with me .
They 'll soon be your department , and I 'm sure you 'll handle them well .
But I 'd like you to see them . I 'd like your assistance with them .
Soon you 'll be asking to help me with my experiments .
But I would . I 'd like that more than anything in the world .
Who knows , my dear , perhaps you will .
One day .
I have to go . I have some materials to buy .
Materials for my work .
Well ?
- Here you are , sir . - Careful , man .
Not often we get them perfect in here , sir .
Eyes are generally the first to go .
What do you think , sir ?
They 'll do .
Ten we said , didn 't we ?
- Each . - The pair .
The pair . Just like you said .
- Who is it ? - Paul .
I 'm just coming .
Come in , Paul .
You wanted to see me ?
It 's been a long time since you 've been up here . Why is that ?
- You know you 're always welcome . - I told you I would not help you .
In that case , why do you continue to live here ?
Of course , it 's Elizabeth you 're worried about , isn 't it ?
What is it you want ?
Haven 't you found it difficult keeping away ...
just guessing what I was doing ?
Never knowing how well I was getting on ?
I 've decided to let you see my progress .
Then you can judge for yourself whether I shall succeed or not .
I 'm at the last stage but one , come and see .
- What do you think ? - It 's horrible !
Paul , the features are not important .
What matters is I 'm creating a being that will live and breathe .
Once the scars on the face heal , it won 't look so bad .
Victor , I appeal to you .
Stop what you 're doing before it 's too late .
What am I doing ?
I 'm harming nobody .
Just robbing a few graves . What doctor or scientist doesn 't ?
How else can we learn the complexities of the human animal ?
Doctors rob for the eventual good of mankind .
This can never end in anything but evil .
Why do you say that ?
I admit he isn 't a particularly good-looking specimen at present .
One 's facial character is built up by what lies behind it ...
in the brain .
A benevolent mind , and the face assumes the patterns of benevolence .
An evil mind , then an evil face . For this ...
the brain of a genius will be used .
When that brain starts to function within the frame ...
then the face and features will assume wisdom and understanding .
I told you I was at the last stage but one : the brain .
A brain of superior intellect .
A lifetime of knowledge already behind it .
Imagine that .
My creature will be born with a lifetime of knowledge .
Where is this brain to come from ?
I 'll get it .
- Now , Professor . - Lhr or dir .
Your hospitality is too generous , my dear Baron .
On the contrary , Professor Bernstein , it is we who are in your debt .
When Victor told me you could come , I was overjoyed .
You honor me , Miss Elizabeth .
Not only overjoyed because you were to stay with us , but because ...
your presence at dinner tonight would ensure my Victor 's presence .
Elizabeth thinks I spend too much time in my laboratory .
He 's locked in there for hours , Professor . He doesn 't eat and he doesn 't sleep .
I , for one , think the world would be a far better place without research .
At least , my world would be .
She may be right , Baron .
One can spend too much of one 's life locked in stuffy rooms ...
seeking out obscure truths .
Searching , researching ...
until one is too old to enjoy life .
Victor , the Professor is on my side .
You 've failed me , Professor .
Elizabeth will be quoting you when she wants me to leave my work ...
and idle away the time with her .
Indeed , you shall .
I 'll say , " Victor , you are only a little scientist . I shan 't listen to you .
" On the authority of the greatest brain in Europe , leave your laboratory ...
" ... and come out into the sunshine with me . "
Women , Professor . How cleverly they twist our words to suit their own ends .
She 'll only be happy if I give up my work entirely .
Is the world ready for the revelation you scientists make ?
There 's a great difference between knowing a thing is so ...
and knowing how to use that knowledge for the good of mankind .
The trouble with us scientists is ...
we quickly tire of our discoveries .
We hand them over to people who are not ready for them ...
while we go off again into the darkness of ignorance ...
searching for other discoveries ...
which will be mishandled in the same way when the time comes .
It 's not as bad as that , surely .
Would you have us give up research , too ?
Good evening .
Paul , I 'm so glad you arrived in time to meet Professor Bernstein .
Professor Bernstein ?
Yes , indeed . May I introduce my friend Paul Krempe .
- Good evening , sir . - How do you do ?
The Professor is staying with us tonight .
I 'm proud to meet you . I had no idea such an honor awaited my return .
We didn 't expect you until the morning .
I thought it best to come back .
I 've heard a great deal about you from Baron Frankenstein .
I look forward to a talk with you in the morning .
I shall be delighted .
- We 've exhausted the Professor . - No , no .
I have enjoyed every minute of this delightful evening .
But old age comes not alone .
Good night , young lady .
Good night , Professor . I trust that you will sleep well .
- Good night , sir . - Good night .
- I 'll show you to your room . - Thank you .
I really am most honored to have you here , sir .
I 'm most grateful to you , my boy .
You know , I 'm alone in the world .
And to be guest in someone 's home , especially ...
such a charming home like this with such a wonderful atmosphere ...
it 's very precious to me .
You are too kind , sir .
I 'd like to show you a painting just before you retire .
It 's this one at the top of the staircase .
It was purchased by my father and illustrates one of the early operations .
If you step back a little , you 'll see it better .
Look out , Professor ! Look out !
Baron Frankenstein ...
I 'm sure I 'm expressing the feelings of all of us ...
when I say how much we appreciate your kindness and consideration ...
in allowing the body of our poor colleague ...
to find its last resting place in your family vault .
As you know , Professor Bernstein had no living relatives .
It was the least I could do . He was a guest in my house .
I thought I 'd find you here .
That was very intelligent of you .
Now that you 've found me , what do you want ?
You killed the old man , didn 't you ?
And now you 're mutilating his body .
Mutilating ? I 've removed his brain . Mutilating has nothing to do with it .
I can 't prove you murdered him , but I can stop you using his brain .
Why ? He has no further use for it .
- Give me that ! - Don 't be a fool ! Be careful !
You 'll damage it !
Get away from here , leave me alone ! Get out of here !
If you 've damaged it ...
Who is it ?
What 's the matter , Paul ?
I 've come to appeal to you to leave here .
- What are you talking about ? Leave here ? - Now .
This very minute . Before it 's too late .
Paul , we 've been through all this before .
Won 't you understand you 're in real danger ?
What Victor is doing is dangerous to everyone .
Then why do you stay here ? You 're not helping him any longer .
I 'll tell you why I stay here .
I will not leave you alone in this house with him .
Believe me , Paul . You 're wrong about him .
Am I ?
- You must be . - How do you know ?
Have you ever been in that laboratory of his ? No .
You cannot possibly conceive the dreadful thing he 's proposing to do .
What are you trying to tell me ? That Victor is wicked , insane ?
Neither wicked nor insane .
Just so dedicated to his work ...
he can 't see the terrible consequences that could result .
Elizabeth ...
I can 't bear the thought of any harm to you .
I 'd do anything to avoid hurt to you both , but ...
Victor is so wrapped up in his experiments ...
Paul , please .
Please , leave me .
I want you to help me .
You must be mad .
That apparatus was constructed for dual operation . You know that .
I thought I could work it myself , but I can 't .
I 'm delighted .
That means your experiment will not succeed .
You 're going to help me , Paul , whatever you say .
If you help me , once I 've proved my theories , I 'll dispose of this creature .
- How long will that take ? - A month , two at the outside .
And have that thing alive up there ? No !
If you don 't help me , Paul , then I make no such promise .
Somehow , I 'll manage on my own .
However difficult , I 'll do it .
And when I have succeeded ...
I 'll introduce Elizabeth to science and see how she likes it .
There is nothing more important to me than the success of this experiment .
It 's what I 've worked for all my life .
All right , Victor .
I 'll help you .
Victor !
I did it , Paul .
This thing must be destroyed before it regains consciousness .
Do you hear me , Victor ?
- What did you say ? - You must destroy this thing now .
Don 't you see ? I 've succeeded !
Yes , nearly succeeded in getting yourself killed .
- Another 10 seconds and you ... - This is my creation .
Yes , a criminal lunatic . It tried to kill you ...
That 's the brain . When you attacked me , it was damaged .
That makes it your fault , Paul .
Your fault that it is not what I intended it to be .
I can repair the brain .
It 's what I 've done that counts . I 've created a being .
- You promised to destroy it . - When I 've carried out my research .
- Don 't you see you 've created a monster ? - That doesn 't matter .
I shall operate on the brain tomorrow . It shouldn 't take long .
Very well , Victor . Goodbye .
Paul ! Paul !
- Paul , he 's gone ! - He 's what ?
I 've searched the house . Heaven knows where he 's got to .
It 's true , Paul , we must get out and find him !
- I 'll go to the village for help . - No , I 'll send word .
We must pick up his trail .
If he gets into the woods , we 'll never find him .
I 'll meet you downstairs .
Hold on , boy . You 're going too fast for your old grandpa .
You sit here then , Grandpa .
- Where ? - Here .
I 'll go on now . It 's not far .
Aye , thank you , boy .
- Do be careful , now . Go on . - Yes , Grandpa .
That was quick . You can 't have picked many .
What 's the matter ? Can 't you find your way ?
I 'm here , son .
I 've lost my stick . Help me find it , son .
You 're quiet . Cat got your tongue ?
Who are you ?
Tell me who you are .
What do you want with me ? Can 't you see I 'm only a poor blind man ?
I 've got nothing for you .
I can 't harm you .
Somebody help me ! Help me !
Grandpa !
Look , he must have stopped here .
Where did you tell the villagers to make for ?
The south lakeshore . I said we 'd meet them there in half an hour .
Well , his trail is easy to follow anyway .
No , Paul !
- You shoot well . - I 've done what had to be done .
- We 'll bury him before the villagers arrive . - They won 't arrive .
I didn 't send the message .
You madman !
You risked just two of us against that ?
- We might 've been killed ! - We might . But we weren 't .
Now he 's dead , so it doesn 't matter .
Well , it 's done and I hope you 're satisfied .
I 'm satisfied we were in time to stop this monstrous act before it was too late .
If that 's what you mean .
I don 't think I shall ever forgive you for what you 've done . Ever .
- Who 's there ? - It 's me . Paul .
Just a minute .
- Well ? - I 'm leaving now .
- I shall send for my things in a few days . - As you wish , Paul .
- Where are you going ? What will you do ? - I have no idea .
It is no longer necessary for me to remain here .
What do you mean " necessary " ?
Of course , there 's Elizabeth . You stayed to protect her .
You 've done what you set out to do . You can leave with a clear conscience .
I 'll give you life again .
- Justine , you can serve dinner . - Just a minute .
Is it true ?
I beg you pardon ?
About you marrying that woman ?
- Aren 't you forgetting yourself ? - You promised to marry me .
I 'm not forgetting that .
- So I did . - Don 't you laugh at me .
- Stop it ! Stop it or l ... - What ?
- What will you do ? - I 'll kill you .
You stupid little fool !
- Did you really think I 'd marry you ? - You 're hurting !
Get back to your work !
But you 've got to marry me . You 've got to .
I 'm going to have a child .
- Since when is this ? - It doesn 't matter .
It 's true , that 's all .
Why choose me as the father ? Pick any man in the village .
The chances are it 'll be the right one .
She won 't think so . Not when I tell her .
I 'll tell her about what you 're doing in that laboratory of yours .
And then I 'll go to the authorities and tell them .
Tell them what ?
I know plenty , if I care to tell .
- What do you know ? - You wouldn 't like that , would you ?
Well , if you don 't marry me , I 'll tell .
Tell what ?
You know what I 'm talking about .
Proof , my dear . That 's all the authorities would be interested in .
Proof .
- I want you out by tomorrow morning . - I 'll get proof .
Just you see . I 'll get it .
Pass the marmalade , will you , Miss Elizabeth ?
Thank you .
Victor ?
I 'm worried about Justine .
It 's a week since she went away , and we still have no word from her .
I told you not to worry .
I expect some village lothario eloped with her .
She always was a romantic little thing .
How are the wedding invitations coming along ?
- Had any replies yet ? - Yes , quite a few .
- Victor . - Yes , my sweet ?
I 've invited Paul to the wedding . After all , he was your good friend .
I 'm sorry if I 've done wrongly .
He hasn 't accepted yet , so ...
maybe he won 't come .
I hope he does come .
There 's something I 'd like him to see .
To the bride and bridegroom .
To the happy couple .
To the bridesmaids .
- What are you gibbering about ? - I was just rehearsing my speech , my dear .
That 's not until tomorrow , after the wedding .
Yes , I know , my dear , but these things take time .
Come on . We 're going home .
So soon ?
Come on .
Thank heavens they 're gone . I have work to do upstairs .
But this is our wedding eve . I thought ...
Oh , come , Elizabeth . We are not sentimental young lovers .
Can I come and watch you working in your laboratory ?
No , my dear . Not yet . But one day very soon .
I promise you .
It 's a pity Paul didn 't come .
Leave those for the morning , Ellen .
Yes , Miss Elizabeth .
Good evening . I 'm Herr Krempe .
Are the Baron and Miss Elizabeth at home ?
- Yes . - Paul !
- Paul , how marvelous to see you ! - Elizabeth !
- We thought you weren 't coming . - You look wonderful !
- And Victor ? - He is in his laboratory .
He 's been almost living there for the past few weeks .
- What 's he doing ? - As if I should know .
I 'll never know what goes on behind that locked laboratory door .
Of course , I forgot .
He 'll be pleased to see you , because he said yesterday ...
that he wished you were here because he has something he wants you to see .
- Has he ? - Why don 't you go and surprise him ?
I will .
- Who 's there ? - Paul .
Paul ?
Paul .
Still keeping the door locked . Is that necessary ?
You can judge for yourself in a moment .
Elizabeth said you had something to show me .
Yes .
Yes , Paul , I have .
I 've started on brain surgery , Paul .
Nothing to say ?
- So it wasn 't killed . - Oh , it was .
At least , life had passed from its body . But don 't forget ...
I put it there in the first place . It was easy to restore .
Wait , Paul . I want to show you something else .
- I 've seen enough . - Wait , Paul !
Watch this .
Get up !
Come on , get up !
That 's right .
Now come here .
Come on now .
Come here !
Sit .
Sit down .
Sit down !
Is this your creature of superior intellect ?
Your perfect physical being , this animal !
Ask it a question of advanced physics .
It 's got a brain with a lifetime of knowledge , it should find it simple .
Shall I tell you something , Paul ?
There you see the result of your handiwork as much as mine .
Oh , yes . I gave him life . I put a brain in his head .
I chose a good brain , a brilliant one .
But you damaged it . You put a bullet in the wretched thing .
This is your fault , Paul . Do you understand that ?
Your fault .
Yes , I understand .
But you won 't win , Paul . Shall I tell you why you won 't win ?
Because I shall carry on .
If I can 't cure it by brain surgery , then I 'll get another brain .
And another . And another .
No . No , you will not .
Paul , what are you going to do ?
For your sake , and to protect Elizabeth , I 've so far kept silent .
Now I shall go to the authorities and have them destroy that creature .
- And see that you pay for these atrocities . - No !
Paul , where are you going ?
Paul , wait a minute ! What are you going to gain by this ?
- You 're as much a part of it as I. - I 've had nothing to do with it for months .
I 've got something to say .
Who 's there ?
I warn you : If you tell the authorities , Elizabeth will be the first to suffer .
Victor ! On the roof .
- We must go up there . - Not this time , I 'm going for help .
Elizabeth ! Come back !
Get back ! Get back !
No ! No !
Get away from me !
My life 's work destroyed .
Destroyed in a moment .
By the same hand that gave it life .
Within half an hour there was nothing left of him .
And that is my story . That is what happened .
You don 't believe me , do you ?
You must believe me . Do you hear ?
A visitor for you , Frankenstein : Herr Krempe . Will you see him ?
Oh , yes ! I knew Paul wouldn 't fail me .
He 'll tell you it 's true . He knows .
He 'll tell you it 's true !
All right , he 'll see you .
I knew Paul wouldn 't fail me . He 's been a good friend .
He 'll prove everything I said is true . He knows .
My dear friend , Paul !
Paul !
Paul , my friend , tell them , Paul .
- Tell them what , Victor ? - About him . About the creature I made .
Tell them . You were the only person to see him apart from myself and Justine .
The girl you murdered .
But I didn 't . That 's what I 've been saying . It was him .
- He did it . - Who ?
- Who did it , Victor ? - The creature I made .
You know . The man . Tell them .
Oh , no ! No , Paul !
Paul , you must tell them .
You know what 's going to happen . Only you can save me .
You must tell them .
Paul , I 'll make you ! I 'll make you !
Paul , you must tell them ! Paul !
You must tell them . Paul !
I 'm sorry , Paul , but you must tell them .
You must save me , Paul .
You 've got to save me !
No !
Paul !
There is nothing we can do for him now .
Come on , I 'll take you home .